Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adopted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
[translators] Carsen and Maxwell
[to join mailing list] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[to sponsor our project] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For all the lovers in the world,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For all the lovers in the world,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
[translators] Carsen and Maxwell
[to join mailing list] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[to sponsor our project] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
The Household Department now
sends us only the best of everything.
Everyone knows how much His Majesty likes you, My Lady.
He also instructed Mr Wen to make tonics for you every day.
You'd think it as a treat.
The medicine is all bitterness.
Speaking of bitterness,
Yu has been cursing you bitterly since her demotion.
Let her be.
I have a clear conscience.
Her curses won't be fulfilled.
But they are too unpleasant to hear.
What about I report it to the Empress?
She'll hold Yu responsible.
That's more trouble than it's worth.
"Forgive a mistake when you can."
She'll be fine after a while.
That is very kind of you, My Lady.
My Lady, the medicine is ready.
The recent tonics taste very sour.
Mr Wen might have added new ingredients into it.
It hasn't been long since I got up,
but I feel sleepy again.
You've been sleeping a lot lately.
Help me get ready for a nap.
Jade,
when did I begin to sleep excessively?
About five days ago.
You sleep for almost half of the day lately.
It was around 9 am when His Majesty came here last time,
but you were still asleep ...
You also think there's something amiss, don't you?
Let me send for Mr Wen before you nap.
Go discreetly.
Say it's just a routine check.
Pardon me, My Lady.
This is going to sting slightly.
This is the Hegu acupuncture point.
The needle will indicate unusual sleepiness.
It changes color under the effect of certain drugs.
As we expected, the tonics were tampered with.
My Lady, the tip of the needle turned into light green.
What is that? Poison?
It's not that.
Someone increased the dosage
of one ingredient in the prescribed tonics.
They have been very discreet about the dosage.
It is too subtle to come to my attention between routine visits.
But if you take the medicine for a long period of time,
you will experience excessive somnolence at first
and psychotic delirium in under six months.
What a brilliant move!
They surely hold me in high regard.
It's fortunate that we discovered it.
I will prescribe treatments for you, My Lady.
This is a sinister trick. Clearly this person
attempts to subject you to death, My Lady.
Rivalries in the harem are always taken to extremes.
We can never be too effective in the defense.
Mr Wen, I would die a mysterious death without your help.
It was my negligence that caused you suffering, My Lady.
I will be particularly careful in the future.
I will prepare and serve the tonics in person
to prevent any form of meddling.
It's important to take precautions,
but the priority should be identifying the poisoner.
The tonics were prepared in my palace according to your prescriptions.
It must be my servants.
There were new servants sent to your palace last month.
The tonics were contaminated after that.
In that case, we will have to pay attention to the new servants.
What is your plan, My Lady?
I hope Mr Wen would like to put on a show with me.
We will act as if nothing happened,
not to beat the grass and alert the snakes.
Yes, My Lady.
(raising her voice) Thank you, Mr Wen.
I'm pleased to hear that I'm all right.
It is usual to feel fatigued in the spring.
You might as well take the opportunity to get more rest.
Thank you, sir.
My Lady, I found a movable brick on the courtyard wall.
It wasn't there until recently.
"Trouble resides behind one's own screen walls."
Keep it to yourself.
Watch the courtyard with Xiao-Yunzi
when they brew the medicine tomorrow.
They'll be caught red-handed.
Yes, My Lay.
Xiao-Yunzi knows kungfu.
He won't let the turncoats get away.
I bow in respect before Your Majesty.
I bow in respect before Your Highnesses.
Rise.
Have a seat.
I thank Your Majesty.
I can finally put my mind at ease
seeing Lady Shen in good health.
Lady Shen's accidental fall
turned out to be a blessing in disguise.
It regained her visitations from His Majesty,
which some of us could only wish for.
Indeed.
I was wondering why people were
swarming to the Thousand Carp Pond.
But I got my head around it afterwards.
They must have been expecting a plop
to fall into His Majesty's arms.
That is funny, Concubine Beauté.
Who would imperil their own life?
Of course,
Lady Shen has been highly favored,
unlike the old women who
turn over every stone to attract His Majesty.
Your Highness's words scared me.
We will all live to the day when we are old.
I will pray to the Buddha in the Baohua Hall
for eternal youthfulness like Your highness.
The Buddha has too many prayers to answer.
What we do matters more than what we pray.
I heard that Lady Sourire was always
by your side when you were unwell.
I wonder where she is today.
Lady Sourire abandoned her sister
when invited by His Majesty's to his study.
That's why she's absent today.
I see.
Such is the sisterhood in the palace.
We were on watch when they brew the tonic.
Violet was watching the stove and no one else was around.
It's contaminated.
I beg your pardon for our negligence, My Lady.
It's not entirely your fault.
The tonic was poisoned right under your nose
without anyone else accessing the pot.
There must be something amiss.
Jade, discard the tonic secretly.
What are you looking at?
I was thinking, if the poison wasn't
added during the brewing process,
there must be something wrong with the utensils.
Let me have a look.
I don't see anything wrong with it.
Are we thinking of it the wrong way?
Look,
the color of the lid seems to be darker than the pot.
Aiyo, it is.
You can spot the difference if you look closely.
Why is that?
Is it because the lid was simmered in the poison
to have absorbed the color of the poison?
The tonic comes into contact with the lid when it boils.
That is how the poison made its way into the tonic.
(snort) What sophistication!
No wonder our efforts were to no avail.
They have been "keeping a lid" on it.
Who is taking care of the utensils?
It used to be me, but I
gave them to Spica, the newcomer.
- Xiao-Yunzi.
- Yes.
Discard the tonic and put the pot back.
Do it discreetly.
And inquire about Spicas's background for me.
Mr Yun.
Spica, why did you sneak behind my back?
Mr Yun, what brings you to the kitchen?
I hope you can pardon the sootiness.
I am the head eunuch of the palace.
I go anywhere I want.
Why are you still using that shabby pot to brew tonics for My Lady?
It looks as if My Lady had fallen from grace.
Get a new one immediately.
Sir, you might not know that an older pot brews better tonics.
A new pot reduces the potency of the medicine.
You know better, don't you?
We'll keep the pot for now.
Keep up the good work.
Oh, My Lady is napping after the morning tonic.
You should prepare the evening tonic soon.
My Lady, Spica used to work for Escort Yu.
She was one of the maids
that were sent away upon Yu's demotion.
Interesting.
An avenger for Yu.
What a loyal maid to her former mistress.
Bring her here to see me.
Yes.
Ah, get some of burning charcoals from the kitchen.
They will be come in handy.
Good to see you here, Jade.
The evening tonic is almost ready.
It's okay, I will stay here for a bit.
Mr Wen selected the best medicine for My Lady.
I've been watching it carefully.
Spica, you are very loyal to My Lady as a newcomer.
It is an honor to serve Lady Sourire.
I must do my best.
My Lady appreciates your hard work.
She wishes to reward you.
You should go quickly.
My Lady wishes to reward me?
Go quickly.
My Lady is waiting.
Bring the stove to keep the tonic warm.
Raise your head.
We won't eat you.
Don't be scared.
I simply wish to talk to you.
Jinxi told me that you have been a competent maid.
I appreciate that.
I wonder what I should reward you
so that the other servants will follow your example.
Thank you, My Lady.
I simply did my job.
You stand out from the newcomers to my palace.
I wonder which concubine you used to work for.
Why would she send you away?
I was too humble to work for any notable concubine.
I am honored to be your maid.
It must be the good karma from my past lives.
Escort Yu is not a notable concubine
due to her demotion.
But what did she offer you
to make you commit the heinous crime?
I did serve Escort Yu,
but I have no idea what you're talking about, My Lady.
You don't know what I'm talking about?
What happened to the lid of my brew pot?
I have no idea!
I am loyal to you, My Lady!
If you say so, we will give you
a chance to prove your loyalty.
My Lady has to be cautious
for you have worked for Escort Yu.
You can prove your innocence and loyalty
by holding a charcoal in your hand.
And we all will treat you nicely.
Do it!
You are scared, aren't you?
How fake your loyalty is!
Please spare me, My Lady.
Please spare me!
Tell me the truth,
or you will be flogged to death.
One day, after I was sent to the Palace of Pearl Jade,
Escort Yu asked me to see her.
She gave me a lot of money
and forced me to do this for her.
I'm such a fool, My Lady!
I beg your forgiveness, My Lady!
Go on, this is your chance to atone for your crime.
But I won't tolerate a word of dishonesty.
Escort Yu said all I needed to do
was to put poison in your tonics and food.
I made a moving brick on the wall
at Yu's command.
She had messages and objects
passed to me through the hole.
That is how the poison was passed in?
And she taught you to simmer the lid with the poison?
Do you have any accomplices?
No, there's no one else!
When does Yu send in messages and the poison?
Hmm ...
Xiao-Yunzi, put the charcoal in her mouth!
I'll say! I'll say!
She sends in the poison every other day.
I'll go to pick it up.
Every other day?
So tonight?
What time is the pick-up?
Is there any code word?
At 7 pm, there goes cuckoo on the other side of the wall.
I will make a cuckoo sound in response.
Did you see who that was?
No, I couldn't see.
But I know it's a man from his hand.
There's a scar in the palm of his right hand.
Xiao-Yunzi, tie her up in the storeroom.
Keep her alive.
Say she's sent to Lady Shen if anyone asks.
Go!
Jinxi, you will pick up the poison in place of Spica.
Select a few eunuchs to assist Xiao-Yunzi.
Yes, I'll go get ready.
I need to tell Meizhuang about this.
Yes, it's a good idea to plan with Lady Shen.
What about Companion An?
Let's not give trouble to her faint heart.
Certainly.
You must make up your mind, My Lady.
Don't compromise yourself this time!
My Lady, Xiao-Yunzi is up on the roof.
He'll jump and catch the culprit.
I'll be standing by the wall.
It's good that Xiao-Yunzi knows kungfu.
He's well disguised by the darkness.
[to join mailing list] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[to sponsor our project] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Got him!
Xiao-Yunzi, we got him!
Go, go quickly!
Go get him!
Go!
- Let me go! I'm begging of you!
- Be quiet!
- Let me go!
- Please let me go!
- On your knees!
My Lady, please let me go!
Hold up his head.
I'm afraid it's an old friend.
Xiao-Yinzi?
Mr Yin, I trust you've been well.
Peace to Lady Sourire.
We used to be mistress and servant.
You will just need to answer my questions.
Are the sticks in place?
Yes, My Lady.
Who do you work for currently?
For Escort Yu.
That must be a waste of your talent.
I don't feel that way.
A servant doesn't get to pick his mistress.
It's good that you can look on the bright side of life.
Didn't you follow your shifu to work for Concubine Beauté?
Why were you sent to Escort Yu?
Shifu offended Concubine Beauté
for his intention to work for you.
Concubine Beauté began to disdain me as well.
Her Highness sent me to serve Escort Yu
as a chance to redeem myself.
She thinks long-term for you, doesn't she?
Now tell me, what were you doing
outside my palace at this time?
I ...
- Xiao-Yunzi.
- Yes.
Slap this ungrateful turncoat
until he speaks the truth.
Please spare me, My Lady!
My Lady ...
please spare me ... My Lady!
I am telling the truth!
Please spare me!
My Lady, that weasel confessed everything under torture.
He said that Escort Yu instructed him to come here.
Tie him up in the storeroom as well.
Keep watch on him and Spica.
I feel bitterly, bitterly disappointed.
I treated him so nicely.
Don't feel disappointed by that trash.
Now it is clear that Yu took revenge grudgingly.
I have been extremely tolerant of Yu.
But when I give her an inch, she takes an ell.
Meizhuang, why is it so difficult
to have some peace in the palace?
"One has no intention of harm
while the tiger does."
You and I, we never meant to harm anyone.
But they want to take our lives.
I have to report this to His Majesty and the Empress.
There's no refuting of the concrete evidence against Yu.
But I'm afraid His Majesty would still have feelings for her.
She might be excused from death
for her futile attempt to poison and curse My Lady.
But deception of His Majesty is a capital offence.
My Lady, do you remember that I asked you whether
"fish eyes were passed off as pearls" on New Year's Eve?
Your Highness ...
What is so urgent?
Xiao-Yinzi didn't return to Yu last night.
I was just informed that
he has been kept in the Palace of Pearl Jade.
Useless eunuch!
Your Highness, that castrated pig must have
confessed everything under torture.
Escort Yu will be held responsible.
What if she rat us out?
What do you suggest?
Finish one to finish all.
No,
it will be suspicious to make a move right now.
She has to take this to her grave.
She wanted to kill Zhen Huan for herself.
Why would she choose to help us over a chance to survive?
She would choose her family's survival over her own.
Why did you take so long?
I had to try to make it clear.
I'm not an articulate maid.
Says your silver tongue.
You not only need to make it clear,
but also appeal to His Majesty emotionally.
Thank you for your advice, sir.
Aiyo, don't do that to an old friend!
What did His Majesty say?
You'll listen for yourself.
I'll be much obliged for your help.
Su Peisheng!
Who are you?
How dare you break into my palace?
Yu is banished to the Cold Palace
by His Majesty's decree.
I don't believe this!
I need to see His Majesty!
His Majesty has no intention to see you!
Go!
I don't believe this!
I need to see His Majesty!
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
- Rise.
- I thank Your Majesty.
Did you sleep well last night?
I thank Your Majesty.
It was dangerous to sleep too well.
I understand.
Jinxi has reported to me and the Empress.
I will have your tonics and food
closely monitored in the future.
This will never happen again.
It was also my fault to be oblivious.
It wasn't your fault.
It was the bitter rivalry beyond imagination.
Spica and Xiao-Yinzi were flogged to death.
And Yu will be confined to the Cold Palace
for the rest of her life.
Huan Huan, you are out of harm's way.
I never meant to vie with anyone.
So many people died
for my unintentional offence to Yu.
I am a sinful concubine,
unworthy of Your Majesty's favor.
Don't overthink.
You've been the innocent victim to a series of appalling events.
Take it easy on yourself.
I made a wish on New Year's Eve
that the northern wind could spare the blooming plums.
But that ended up unfulfilled.
Where did you make the wish?
And what did you say for your wish?
In the Garden of Leaning Plums.
I wished “If the northern wind can hear the plum flowers,
spare the blooming wishes for a peaceful spring."
I remember wetting my shoes in the snow that night.
Did you run into anyone?
Si Lang, how did you know?
That night, in the garden,
I ran into a male stranger.
As I was out without permission
and had to avoid contact with a male stranger,
I got away saying that I was a maid working in the garden.
Was the stranger that night ...
I apologize for my ill manners.
I didn't know it was Your Majesty.
It was you?
So it was you!
I mistook her.
Su Peisheng!
Yes, Your Majesty.
Make the announcement that
Yu in the Cold Palace is granted options for suicide
for deceiving me and poisoning a concubine.
Yes, I'll do it immediately.
What was wrong?
Why would Your Majesty grant her suicide?
She lied to me, saying that
she was the person who spoke to me that night.
She became a concubine because of that,
and caused offence to her superiors time and again.
Now her crimes are unpardonable.
She made mistakes because she admired Your Majesty.
An emperor's words count.
She is unpardonable.
But if you plead her case,
I will allow her corpse to be sent home.
I thank Your Majesty.
Did you bring any luck charm with you
to the garden that night?
like a sachet, a fan pendant, or a hairpin?
Just a trinket I liked.
I can make another one for Si Lang if you like.
You've been unnerved lately.
Worry about that when you get over it.
I'm in no hurry to spend decades with you.
There was one more thing I summoned you for.
The Ministry of Revenue proposed
a new farmland planning measure.
Opinions vary about the proposal.
I'd rather go investigate by myself
than listen to the endless debates.
I'll go to the suburbs.
The trip will take a few days.
Farming is a matter of life and death for the people.
When will Your Majesty leave?
I can leave right away.
Please take the best care of yourself
during the trip.
I wanted to go with Su Peisheng,
but it's not so convenient for a eunuch.
But don't worry, I traveled a lot for
the prior emperor as the State Prince.
Take care of yourself.
I'll be back in no time.
How is Lady Cao's job going?
She's been a quiet person,
but she talks sense whenever she speaks.
She's been taking care of Yu's family.
That is very thoughtful of her.
What use will she be
if she can't even sort things out for Your Highness?
But you used to be a
more favored concubine of His Majesty.
Why's that different now?
Because she has a daughter.
That gets her to see His Majesty oftener.
True, even if it is a daughter.
Why is everyone so quiet today?
I feel suffocated.
What's wrong?
I hate being ambushed,
and I was resentful of Spica and Xiao-Yinzi.
But when His Majesty executed them,
it didn't ease my mind.
Me neither.
No ones would take heart from the death of another.
There is yet one after another to be defeated.
Then we'll deal with one after another.
They will be defeated as long as
we are of one heart and one mind.
But Sourire, why would you keep this from me?
It was not until this morning that
I heard about it from the Empress.
I didn't meant to hide anything from you.
It's better to hear nothing of such a frightful incident.
But I see you as my own sister.
Sisters would share cares and burdens.
It's fortunate that this is over.
I'm grateful that you are all right.
His Majesty has granted suicide to Yu.
That is the fate for any intender of harm.
Soft-spoken as she is,
Lingrong has a strong mind.
My Lady!
Yu refuses to commit suicide.
She kicked up a tremendous row in the Cold Palace
yelling that she has to see His Majesty before she dies.
How?
His Majesty must have left the palace by now.
It's impossible to keep her alive
until His Majesty comes back.
Is it reported to the Empress?
Her Majesty has been bed-ridden with cephalalgia lately.
We can't count on her.
In that case, there's only
Consort Fleur that we can count on ...
Her Highness said that she's been indisposed.
She was close with Yu.
Now she wouldn't have the least connection with her.
Yu insists that she's been slandered.
She insanely smashed the poison granted to her.
She even curses My Lady
blatantly and viciously in the Cold Palace.
Let her be.
Last-ditch protest.
Sourire, I think it's time that I should go.
- Take care.
- Goodbye, Lingrong.
Cuckoo, what is the Cold Palace?
It the palace for the banished concubines.
Many of them ended up dead or psychotic
during their confinement.
It is considered a haunted place.
So no one visits the Cold Palace?
What the hell of a place is that?
Servants near the Cold Palace repeatedly saw
ghosts that kept crying night after night.
It's horrifying.
I will go for a check.
My Lady, let's not go inside.
It gives me the creeps.
(Let me go! Let go!)
Let me go! Let go of me!
Yu, accept your fate.
Let me go!
Let go!
Why did you come here, Companion An?
Sourire heard that Yu has been cursing her.
She sent me here to look into it.
Le me go! Let go!
It seems that you haven't finished the job, sir?
She's untamed.
Why are you here?
Why are you here!
Where is His Majesty?
Let me go!
Pull her away!
Why would His Majesty
set his noble foot on the Cold Palace?
It was all because of Zhen Huan!
It was all that bitch!
She wooed His Majesty into killing me!
I suppose you wish to know
why you are granted suicide, don't you?
I'll do the favor to tell you.
It was you that had Sourire's tonics poinsoned, wasn't it?
Yes, I arranged that.
But it was her who made me fall from grace
to this humble existence!
I wish to drink her blood and chew her bones.
I wish that bitch will live in hell life after life.
You wish?
You don't even get to have a wish
when winner takes all.
No, I must not die.
I encountered His Majesty on New Year's Eve.
His Majesty likes to hear me sing Kunqu Opera.
He wouldn't let me die.
“If the northern wind can hear the plum flowers,
spare the blooming wishes for a peaceful spring."
You pretended to be Sourire on New Year's Eve.
Have you no shame?
It was her ... It was her!
No, I must not die.
I must not die!
Your Majesty ... Your Majesty ...
You like my Kunqu Opera.
May I have a word with you, sir?
I will sing Kunqu for Your Majesty!
My Lady.
(Your Majesty ...)
His Majesty is away while the Empress
is having a seizure of cephalalgia.
This madness must be stopped.
Your Majesty ...
My Lady, Yu was granted suicide.
But this madwoman smashed
the cup of poison and tore up the silk noose.
There's nothing we can do about her.
Sir, you have served His Majesty for long, haven't you?
Yes, for over 30 years.
Sir, you are a most knowledgeable person in the palace and much appreciated for you hard work.
You understand His Majesty the best.
Now that His Majesty is away,
should we keep her alive until he returns?
Would you suggest ...
Sir, your work is done when she is dead.
No one would investigate how she dies.
For instance, what would happen if a concubine refused
to be buried alive with a deceased emperor?
My Lady, I understand.
Sir, I hope you understand
"one has more dreams the longer he sleeps".
It puts an end to His Majesty's concern
when you terminate her life.
Yes, I bid you goodbye, My Lady.
Your Majesty ...
Help me, Your Majesty!
Zhen Huan, you will be terminated,
whether by me or not!
You will go to hell!
What impenitence at death!
Yu will die for sure, but why would you
make a trip to this spooky place, My Lady?
I want Sourire to know that
there's something I can do for her.
You end up with eunuchs,
who you never treated as humans.
- Xiao-Xiazi.
- Yes.
We had to be tolerant of her,
but not anymore.
No! No!
I am a concubine.
You cannot kill me!
Peace to Lady Sourire.
Peace to Lady Shen.
I wish to report to you that Yu committed suicide.
Good that it's over.
Just a twang on the bowstring.
Nothing to worry about, My Lady.
What bowstring?
My Lady, you sent Companion An to check, didn't you?
Yu was untamable, and
Companion An suggested we strangle her.
You strangled her?
Yes.
It was Companion An's idea?
Shifu wouldn't have thought of that otherwise.
But no one likes Yu.
We won't tell anyone.
- Nicely done. You can go now.
- I bid you goodbye.
- My Lady.
- Are you all right?
Are you all right, My Lady?
What the bloody hell did he say that for?
My Lady, the smell
of the incense will make you fell better.
Peace to Companion An.
Where's Sourire?
My Lady is having tea with Lady Shen.
I will report that you are here.
It's okay. I feel like some tea as well.
I'll see myself in.
Meizhuang, did I went too far in this?
"Do unto others as you would be done."
But I couldn't imagine that
Lingrong was so hard-hearted about it.
Lingrong did it for us.
Killings are all too common in the palace.
One has a harder heart while another does not.
I know, but it all started because of you.
Lingrong wasn't involved in this.
Even so, she had Yu strangled in the Cold Palace.
That is not the sensitive girl I know.
[translators] Carsen and Maxwell
[to join mailing list] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[to sponsor our project] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.